<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Brad Thornborrow</title><link>/</link><description>Recent content on Brad Thornborrow</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>IPC Annual Report Education Resources</title><link>/posts/2019/08/ipc-annual-report-education-resources/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2019/08/ipc-annual-report-education-resources/</guid><description>Earlier this summer, the Information and Privacy Commissioner (IPC) of Ontario released their 2018 Annual Report . One of the more interesting stories in the report concerned Privacy Order PO-3617. This order related to a lengthy dispute between the Ontario Medical Association (OMA) and Toronto Star, who requested the release of the top 100 OHIP billing physicians in Ontario. In April of this year, the Supreme Court of Canada dismissed the OMA’s appeal and allowed for the release of this information, which many have seen as a victory for government openness and transparency.</description></item><item><title>Automating Jekyll site updates with GitLab CI Schedules</title><link>/posts/2018/10/automating-jekyll-site-updates-with-gitlab-ci-schedules/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/10/automating-jekyll-site-updates-with-gitlab-ci-schedules/</guid><description>One of the earliest posts I made on this site described the process I used to automate daily updates using a Raspberry Pi server running Raspbian. With my recent move of the site to GitLab Pages , I was able to automate daily site updates without the need of an external server. This was made possible through the magic of the GitLab CI (Continuous Integration) Scheduling.
For those not familiar with GitLab Pages, it uses a CI configuration file (.</description></item><item><title>Create Twitterbot API Access Tokens using Twurl</title><link>/posts/2018/08/create-twitterbot-api-access-tokens-using-twurl/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/08/create-twitterbot-api-access-tokens-using-twurl/</guid><description>If you do a quick Google search for &amp;ldquo;twitterbot&amp;rdquo;, you&amp;rsquo;ll find countless articles outlining the steps to setup a Twitterbot account and create the necessary Twitter API keys using this account. Unfortunately, with the recent Twitter Developer platform changes, they have significantly restricted the Developer approval process. In this new environment, it makes little sense to setup a separate Developer account for the purposes of a single Twitterbot (and in all likelihood, the request may be denied by Twitter anyway).</description></item><item><title>The Mac Pro is dead, long live the Mac Mini?</title><link>/posts/2018/08/the-mac-pro-is-dead-long-live-the-mac-mini/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/08/the-mac-pro-is-dead-long-live-the-mac-mini/</guid><description>I try to avoid opinion pieces, but with the rumours this week that Apple is reportedly updating the Mac Mini this fall , I needed to get my thoughts on the subject off my chest.
I think it is has been clear for a while that Apple has not been paying close attention to the Mac lineup. For example, in the recent Apple quarterly earnings report, Mac sales showed a 13% year-over-year decline.</description></item><item><title>Twitter Developer Platform process changes</title><link>/posts/2018/08/twitter-developer-platform-process-changes/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/08/twitter-developer-platform-process-changes/</guid><description>If you are any kind of Web developer, you have likely heard all about the changes Twitter has made to their Developer Platform. Primarily, the changes impact developers of 3rd party Twitter apps due to the removal of several legacy API endpoints, such as the Tweet streaming and Direct Messaging APIs. These changes have received a lot of coverage, but there has been little said about the impact for small in-house and student application developers.</description></item><item><title>Build a Twitter Message of the Day (MOTD) Bot</title><link>/posts/2018/07/build-a-twitter-message-of-the-day-motd-bot/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/07/build-a-twitter-message-of-the-day-motd-bot/</guid><description>I was first introduced to the concept of the message of the day (MOTD) while working as a SunOS system administrator back in my university days. At our school, the systems used the Unix fortune command to display random messages and quotes on login. Being a bit nostalgic about these early days of the personal computer era, I decided to build a Message of the Day bot for Twitter. This would give me the pleasure of seeing my own custom messages of the day in my feed, and help me learn the ins and outs of the Twitter API.</description></item><item><title>What Happened to Windows Update?</title><link>/posts/2018/07/what-happened-to-windows-update/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/07/what-happened-to-windows-update/</guid><description>Recently, my wife mentioned she was seeing some warning on her computer that it was almost out of disk space. I thought this odd as her system has a 500GB SSD, and last I checked it still had over 400GB free. To play it safe, I took a quick look at her system and found it had a new (and unknown) drive labeled D: with just under 50MB available. This was the drive causing the Low Disk Space warning.</description></item><item><title>Using PowerShell to Find Inactive Users in AD and Exchange</title><link>/posts/2018/07/using-powershell-to-find-inactive-users-in-ad-and-exchange/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/07/using-powershell-to-find-inactive-users-in-ad-and-exchange/</guid><description>Recently, I was working with a client to consolidate of several Active Directory and LDAP domains into a single unified domain. To ensure we were starting with a clean slate, one of the first steps I performed was an audit to find any inactive accounts in the Active Directory domains. This allowed the client to investigate and/or remove any stale accounts prior to consolidation. There are many professional (and possibly expensive) tools which can be used to automate this process, but for small to mid-sized domains, this can be done fairly easily using the following PowerShell command and some Excel manipulation.</description></item><item><title>Simple script to monitor for website changes</title><link>/posts/2018/06/simple-script-to-monitor-for-website-changes/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/06/simple-script-to-monitor-for-website-changes/</guid><description>As I may have mentioned in previous posts, I run several small websites, both professionally and for personal interests. The majority are simple static websites, or low volume blogs which only expect a couple of updates in a week. With the various issues recently of crypto-miners and other exploits, I wanted a process in place to monitor for site issues, especially if the site changed unexpectedly. Of course, I could setup a trigger using IFTTT to monitor the sites and notify me in the event of changes, but as always, I wanted a “home-grown” solution I could customize.</description></item><item><title>Moving your Jekyll site from GitHub Pages to GitLab</title><link>/posts/2018/06/moving-your-jekyll-site-from-github-pages-to-gitlab/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/06/moving-your-jekyll-site-from-github-pages-to-gitlab/</guid><description>For the last several months, I&amp;rsquo;ve been pondering the move of this site from GitHub Pages to GitLab. I have several reasons which I won&amp;rsquo;t get into here, but the recent news regarding the acquisition of GitHub by Microsoft gave me the impetus to get this done. I ran into several interesting &amp;ldquo;hiccups&amp;rdquo; during the process, and decided to write this post to help anyone else going down this road.</description></item><item><title>Script for Exporting Micro.blog posts to Jekyll</title><link>/posts/2018/05/script-for-exporting-micro.blog-posts-to-jekyll/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/05/script-for-exporting-micro.blog-posts-to-jekyll/</guid><description>As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned in previous posts, I&amp;rsquo;m a fan of Jekyll for building static websites, but I have also been experimenting with Micro.blog for my personal site. There was a recent discussion on Micro.blog looking for options to mirror posts from Micro.blog to Jekyll. This question stuck with me, and as I already have a Raspberry Pi server in production for handling other daily maintenance tasks, I decided to investigate if this could be done in Python, building on my previous experience.</description></item><item><title>Hosting Media or Files on Amazon S3</title><link>/posts/2018/03/hosting-media-or-files-on-amazon-s3/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/03/hosting-media-or-files-on-amazon-s3/</guid><description>As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned in previous posts, I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of Jekyll for creating static websites. The one obvious shortcoming of Jekyll is the entire site must be regenerated when adding even a single post. Lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been experimenting with Micro.blog for personal posts not appropriate here. It has an iOS app for making quick updates from your phone, and hooks into Twitter and Facebook for automatic cross-posting to your social feeds.</description></item><item><title>Open New Terminal at Folder in macOS</title><link>/posts/2017/10/open-new-terminal-at-folder-in-macos/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2017/10/open-new-terminal-at-folder-in-macos/</guid><description>Previously when I was a Windows user (back in the dark times), I used the Command Prompt Here tool from the Windows 95 PowerToys collection offered by Microsoft. When I transitioned to OS X, I was disappointed there was not a similar option or tool available. Of course, after some research I discovered this was built into the system. I just needed to look in the right place.
To add this function in Finder, open System Preferences, Keyboard, then click on the Shortcuts tab.</description></item><item><title>Hiding Applications from Spotlight in macOS</title><link>/posts/2017/09/hiding-applications-from-spotlight-in-macos/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2017/09/hiding-applications-from-spotlight-in-macos/</guid><description>I have been using OS X (now macOS) for years, yet this simple trick somehow alluded me. Regularly, I would use the standard command + space combination to open Spotlight search, then type photo and press enter, and for whatever reason Photo Booth would open. Similarly, typing type text in Spotlight would open TextEdit instead of Textastic (my current text editor of choice). This was both annoying and perplexing, as I rarely used either application.</description></item><item><title>Binding Automator Scripts to Shortcut keys in macOS</title><link>/posts/2017/08/binding-automator-scripts-to-shortcut-keys-in-macos/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2017/08/binding-automator-scripts-to-shortcut-keys-in-macos/</guid><description>For years after moving from Windows to Mac, I used Karabiner to make my trusty Logitech S510 keyboard act normal in OS X, at least normal from an ex-Windows users perspective. Karabiner also had the added benefit of allowing a standard PC keyboard to mimic other keys, such as the MacBook Eject key. For example, I could bind the eject function to Print Screen, allowing Ctrl + Shift + Print Screen to lock my MacBook quickly from the keyboard.</description></item></channel></rss>