<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>hosting on Brad Thornborrow</title><link>/tags/hosting/</link><description>Recent content in hosting on Brad Thornborrow</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/hosting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Simple script to monitor for website changes</title><link>/posts/2018/06/simple-script-to-monitor-for-website-changes/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/06/simple-script-to-monitor-for-website-changes/</guid><description>As I may have mentioned in previous posts, I run several small websites, both professionally and for personal interests. The majority are simple static websites, or low volume blogs which only expect a couple of updates in a week. With the various issues recently of crypto-miners and other exploits, I wanted a process in place to monitor for site issues, especially if the site changed unexpectedly. Of course, I could setup a trigger using IFTTT to monitor the sites and notify me in the event of changes, but as always, I wanted a “home-grown” solution I could customize.</description></item><item><title>Hosting Media or Files on Amazon S3</title><link>/posts/2018/03/hosting-media-or-files-on-amazon-s3/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/03/hosting-media-or-files-on-amazon-s3/</guid><description>As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned in previous posts, I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of Jekyll for creating static websites. The one obvious shortcoming of Jekyll is the entire site must be regenerated when adding even a single post. Lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been experimenting with Micro.blog for personal posts not appropriate here. It has an iOS app for making quick updates from your phone, and hooks into Twitter and Facebook for automatic cross-posting to your social feeds.</description></item></channel></rss>