<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>twitter on Brad Thornborrow</title><link>/tags/twitter/</link><description>Recent content in twitter on Brad Thornborrow</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/twitter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Create Twitterbot API Access Tokens using Twurl</title><link>/posts/2018/08/create-twitterbot-api-access-tokens-using-twurl/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/08/create-twitterbot-api-access-tokens-using-twurl/</guid><description>If you do a quick Google search for &amp;ldquo;twitterbot&amp;rdquo;, you&amp;rsquo;ll find countless articles outlining the steps to setup a Twitterbot account and create the necessary Twitter API keys using this account. Unfortunately, with the recent Twitter Developer platform changes, they have significantly restricted the Developer approval process. In this new environment, it makes little sense to setup a separate Developer account for the purposes of a single Twitterbot (and in all likelihood, the request may be denied by Twitter anyway).</description></item><item><title>Twitter Developer Platform process changes</title><link>/posts/2018/08/twitter-developer-platform-process-changes/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/08/twitter-developer-platform-process-changes/</guid><description>If you are any kind of Web developer, you have likely heard all about the changes Twitter has made to their Developer Platform. Primarily, the changes impact developers of 3rd party Twitter apps due to the removal of several legacy API endpoints, such as the Tweet streaming and Direct Messaging APIs. These changes have received a lot of coverage, but there has been little said about the impact for small in-house and student application developers.</description></item><item><title>Build a Twitter Message of the Day (MOTD) Bot</title><link>/posts/2018/07/build-a-twitter-message-of-the-day-motd-bot/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/07/build-a-twitter-message-of-the-day-motd-bot/</guid><description>I was first introduced to the concept of the message of the day (MOTD) while working as a SunOS system administrator back in my university days. At our school, the systems used the Unix fortune command to display random messages and quotes on login. Being a bit nostalgic about these early days of the personal computer era, I decided to build a Message of the Day bot for Twitter. This would give me the pleasure of seeing my own custom messages of the day in my feed, and help me learn the ins and outs of the Twitter API.</description></item></channel></rss>