<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>jekyll on Brad Thornborrow</title><link>/tags/jekyll/</link><description>Recent content in jekyll on Brad Thornborrow</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/jekyll/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Automating Jekyll site updates with GitLab CI Schedules</title><link>/posts/2018/10/automating-jekyll-site-updates-with-gitlab-ci-schedules/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/10/automating-jekyll-site-updates-with-gitlab-ci-schedules/</guid><description>One of the earliest posts I made on this site described the process I used to automate daily updates using a Raspberry Pi server running Raspbian. With my recent move of the site to GitLab Pages , I was able to automate daily site updates without the need of an external server. This was made possible through the magic of the GitLab CI (Continuous Integration) Scheduling.
For those not familiar with GitLab Pages, it uses a CI configuration file (.</description></item><item><title>Moving your Jekyll site from GitHub Pages to GitLab</title><link>/posts/2018/06/moving-your-jekyll-site-from-github-pages-to-gitlab/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/06/moving-your-jekyll-site-from-github-pages-to-gitlab/</guid><description>For the last several months, I&amp;rsquo;ve been pondering the move of this site from GitHub Pages to GitLab. I have several reasons which I won&amp;rsquo;t get into here, but the recent news regarding the acquisition of GitHub by Microsoft gave me the impetus to get this done. I ran into several interesting &amp;ldquo;hiccups&amp;rdquo; during the process, and decided to write this post to help anyone else going down this road.</description></item><item><title>Script for Exporting Micro.blog posts to Jekyll</title><link>/posts/2018/05/script-for-exporting-micro.blog-posts-to-jekyll/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2018/05/script-for-exporting-micro.blog-posts-to-jekyll/</guid><description>As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned in previous posts, I&amp;rsquo;m a fan of Jekyll for building static websites, but I have also been experimenting with Micro.blog for my personal site. There was a recent discussion on Micro.blog looking for options to mirror posts from Micro.blog to Jekyll. This question stuck with me, and as I already have a Raspberry Pi server in production for handling other daily maintenance tasks, I decided to investigate if this could be done in Python, building on my previous experience.</description></item></channel></rss>