<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>macos on Brad Thornborrow</title><link>/tags/macos/</link><description>Recent content in macos on Brad Thornborrow</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/macos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Open New Terminal at Folder in macOS</title><link>/posts/2017/10/open-new-terminal-at-folder-in-macos/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2017/10/open-new-terminal-at-folder-in-macos/</guid><description>Previously when I was a Windows user (back in the dark times), I used the Command Prompt Here tool from the Windows 95 PowerToys collection offered by Microsoft. When I transitioned to OS X, I was disappointed there was not a similar option or tool available. Of course, after some research I discovered this was built into the system. I just needed to look in the right place.
To add this function in Finder, open System Preferences, Keyboard, then click on the Shortcuts tab.</description></item><item><title>Hiding Applications from Spotlight in macOS</title><link>/posts/2017/09/hiding-applications-from-spotlight-in-macos/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2017/09/hiding-applications-from-spotlight-in-macos/</guid><description>I have been using OS X (now macOS) for years, yet this simple trick somehow alluded me. Regularly, I would use the standard command + space combination to open Spotlight search, then type photo and press enter, and for whatever reason Photo Booth would open. Similarly, typing type text in Spotlight would open TextEdit instead of Textastic (my current text editor of choice). This was both annoying and perplexing, as I rarely used either application.</description></item><item><title>Binding Automator Scripts to Shortcut keys in macOS</title><link>/posts/2017/08/binding-automator-scripts-to-shortcut-keys-in-macos/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/2017/08/binding-automator-scripts-to-shortcut-keys-in-macos/</guid><description>For years after moving from Windows to Mac, I used Karabiner to make my trusty Logitech S510 keyboard act normal in OS X, at least normal from an ex-Windows users perspective. Karabiner also had the added benefit of allowing a standard PC keyboard to mimic other keys, such as the MacBook Eject key. For example, I could bind the eject function to Print Screen, allowing Ctrl + Shift + Print Screen to lock my MacBook quickly from the keyboard.</description></item></channel></rss>